Guide to the Martinson Family Papers 1921-1958
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Martinson Family Papers
1921-1958
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 059
Martinson family
1.0 linear foot
This collection contains the personal papers of the Martinson family of Missoula, Montana, including records of the Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company, which they owned and operated from the early 1920s to late 1950s.
Biographical Note
Charles A. Martinson was born in Sweden around 1876 and came to America as a small boy. He operated the Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company in Missoula, Montana from 1921 until his death in 1938 at the age of 62. Two years prior to his death, Charles Martinson was severely injured after becoming caught in machinery at the ice plant and never fully recovered. His wife Freda E. Martinson and sons Jack and Karl helped run the company and continued its operation after Charles’ death. Charles A. Martinson and wife Freda Martinson also had a daughter, Jean Gies, married to Anthony Gies of Lewistown, Montana. Freda Martinson was born in 1883 and came to Missoula in 1900, where she resided most of her life. She was visiting Portland at the time of her death in 1958. Jack Martinson enlisted in the Air Force in 1941 and received his commission in 1943. He was a second lieutenant and co-pilot of a B-29 when he was killed during an air raid over Japan in 1945. Anthony Gies also served in the war as a medical technician and was awarded a Bronze Star and an Oak Leaf Cluster in 1945.
The Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company was a retail and wholesale ice and cold storage company from 1921-1958. They supplied ice for ice boxes before more modern refrigerators were common in homes. Ice was cut in blocks from ponds in the Rattlesnake area north of Missoula and stored in sheds with sawdust during the warmer months. The company grew in technology and in 1940 they were able to quick-freeze 1,000 pounds of bread for future consumption by the Forest Service firefighters. This was a huge success because Missoula was experiencing a labor shortage at the time and bakers were unable to meet sudden demands of hundreds of pounds of bread. It was impossible to store bread for more than a day or two before it was discovered that bread kept very well frozen and thawed in good condition. The Missoula Ice Company and the Martinson family home were located on Front Street.
This collection contains the personal papers of the Martinson family of Missoula, Montana, including records of the Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company, which they owned and operated from the early 1920s to late 1950s. The collection is divided into three series. Series I, Martinson family, contains Charles A. Martinson and Freda Martinson’s personal tax returns, personal correspondence from Jack Martinson to family members while he was in the Air Force during World War II, notices of Jack missing in action and killed in action, letters of support and sympathy to the family, military certificates of achievement, awards, and publications, and some of Jack’s personal belongings. Series II, Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company, contains the financial records of the Missoula Ice Company, including check registers, cash disbursement journals, and maps of the property. Series III, photos, includes photos of Jack Martinson and comrades in the Air Force and of the Missoula Ice Company. Photos of the ice company include the building on Front Street, ice sheds, company truck, employees cutting ice from ponds in the Rattlesnake area, and former employees.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Martinson family, 0.5 linear feet, 1921-1951
Series II: Missoula Ice Company, 0.5 linear feet, 1921-1958
Series III: Photos, undated
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and the University of Montana--Missoula.
Donated to the Archives by Mrs. Jean Gies in 1973.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Martinson, C. A. (Charles A.), d. 1938; Martinson, Freda E., d. 1883-1958; Martinson, Jack, d. 1945
Martinson Family
United States--Army Air Forces; Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company
Missoula (Mont.)--Photographs
Cold storage industry. Montana--Missoula; Family-owned business enterprises--Montana--Missoula; Ice industry. Montana--Missoula; Ice industry. Montana--Missoula--Photographs; Swedish Americans--Montana--Missoula; World War, 1939-1945--Personal Narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial Operations, American
Business records--Montana. Missoula; Family papers--Montana. Missoula; Photographs--Montana--Missoula
Labor History; Montana; Missoula; Scandinavian Americans
Businesspeople--Montana--Missoula
- Martinson Family, 1921-1951; Series I; 0.5 linear feet
  - Correspondence to family from Jack Martinson and misc, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - To family from Jack Martinson, 1942 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - To family from Jack Martinson, 1943 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - To family from Jack Martinson, 1944 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - To family from Jack Martinson and to Freda Martinson from Secretary of War and freinds, subject-Jack Martinson missing in action, 1945 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Military Orders, Awards to Jack Martinson and Tony Gies, 1945 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - To Freda MArtinson, from Secretary of War and friends, subject-Jack Martinson killed in action, 1945-1951 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - To family from Jack Martinson, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - C.A. Martinson, Tax Returns, 1921-1933 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - C.A. Martinson, Freda Martinson, Tax Returns, 1934-1945 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Legal documents-Jack’s Air Force Technical School Diploma, Purple Heart Award, and other certificates, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Clippings regarding Jack Martinson and the ice company, 1943-1958 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Jack Martinson’s Pilot Information File, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Miscellaneous-billfold contents, report card, and Air Force publications belonging to Jack Martinson, 1925-1945 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company, 1921-1958; Series II; 0.5 linear feet
  - Check Register, 1921 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Check Register, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Check Register, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Check Register, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Check Register, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Check Register, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Check Register, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Check Register, 1929-1930 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Check Register, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Check Register, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Check Register, 1933-1935 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Check Register, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Check Register, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Check Register, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Check Register, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Check Register, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Check Register, 1948-1955 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Check Register, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Rent Register, 1922-1954 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Maps of Martinson Property, 1938-1954 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Cash Disbursements Journal, 1921-1936 (Volume 1)
  - Cash Receipts, 1921-1931 (Volume 2)
  - Cash Disbursements, 1937-1957 (Volume 2)
- Photos, Series III
  - Missoula Ice and Cold Storage Company, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Missoula Ice Company, 700 Front Street (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.01)
  - Old Barn, Missoula Ice Company, East Front Street (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.02)
  - East Front Street, 6th Block, Duke and King (horses) (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.03)
  - Ice House, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.04)
  - Chris Bosing at warming shack, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.05)
  - Ice Cutting, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake, Missoula, Montana (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.06)
  - Ice Cutting, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake, Missoula, Montana (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.07)
  - Ice Cutting, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake, Missoula, Montana (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.08)
  - Ice Cutting, Ice Pond, Rattlesnake (now Martinwood), Men Removing Ice from Pond (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.09)
  - Ice houses, Diamond T, Harold Nearman in Ice Company Truck (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.10)
  - Harold Nearman (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.11)
  - Tony Dolum (Box-folder 2/14, Photo number 59.III.12)
  - Jack Martinson, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Air Force Men, undated (Box-folder 2/16)